בוקר טוב, Boker tov, ערב ראש השנה, Erev Rosh Hashanah, שנה טובה.
Shana Tova. We are going we are דף ז"ו. daf zayin vav.
We pick up in the middle of ה' עמוד ב'. hey amud
bet. And we pick up with we have now moved to the
next part of the משנה mishnah where the person makes the שבועה
shvuah and the גמרא Gemara that no less than half of it
is his. And the גמרא Gemara just sort of worked through the
exact phrasing of that שבועה. shvuah. And now we take to, we
begin a very important discussion and that is וכי מאחר. Ve-kimei achar.
It's about twelve lines down. Line starts with word פחות מחצי, pachos
mechetzi, maybe fifteen lines
down. Yeah, looks like fifteen lines down. Starts, line starts with word
פחות. pachos. Okay, so three words in. The גמרא Gemara says like
this: וכי מאחר דזה תופס ועומד וזה תופס ועומד שבועה זו למה
Ve-kimei achar she-zeh tofes ve-omed ve-zeh tofes ve-omed, shvuah zu lama? If
this one is grabbing onto it and that one is grabbing onto
it, so they both should have a presumption of being a half
owner. Why do you need the שבועה? shvuah? And this is a
little bit different than the גמרא Gemara earlier because the גמרא Gemara
at the beginning of the מסכת masechet asked like and compared this
to other cases where there wasn't a שבועה shvuah and said how
come sometimes we don't, you know, like if it's definitely going to
come to a false שבועה shvuah or other types of issues and
the גמרא Gemara says well here it won't definitely be false. But
here rather than asking the question about why do we not have
a שבועה, shvuah, it's asking why do we have a שבועה? shvuah?
What's the purpose of this שבועה? shvuah? And we presumably the purpose
of the שבועה shvuah is to you know help clarify the issue,
get somebody to maybe admit or whatever. But the גמרא'ס Gemara's point
here is why do we need that? It's like the facts of
the case seem to speak for themselves. You know, if each one
is holding even though that might not tell you exactly what happened
you know historically, you know, but that should create a presumption of
ownership. So once each one is grabbing on and claiming it's theirs,
that should create a presumption of ownership. Why, why is there a
need to actually additionally make them make have them make a שבועה?
shvuah? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan,
so we saw this quoted before, שבועה זו תקנת חכמים היא שלא
יהא כל אחד ואחד הולך ותוקף בטליתו של חבירו ואומר שלי הוא.
shvuah zo takanat chachamim hi shelo yehei kol echad ve-echad holech ve-tokef
be-talito shel chaveiro ve-omer sheli hu. It's really not so much to
clarify the issue in terms of the facts. Each one has a
חזקה, chazakah, we should just split it. It's really more preventative because
we don't want to create anarchy that anybody can just grab something
and say it's mine and then you say okay you're holding onto
it you get it or you get half of it or whatever.
So in this type of a case the fact that the person
knows he'll have to make a שבועה shvuah hopefully will prevent them
from doing such an act. Or and or once they find out
that they have to make a שבועה shvuah it'll get them to
you know to renounce their claim. So now this leads the גמרא,
Gemara, so that's an idea we saw before, but this now leads
the גמרא Gemara to get back also to an idea that was
introduced at the beginning which is how helpful do we think a
שבועה shvuah will be if a person is willing to steal? Okay,
because at the beginning of the גמרא Gemara the emphasis was that
a person will rationalize. Okay, and the שבועה shvuah will get the
person to stop their rationalizing when they realize that they have to
really say it in a definitive way and take an oath to
it. They're not just sort of telling themselves a story, well I
deserve it even if it's not really mine. Okay, but here we're
saying we're afraid not that a person is going to rationalize, but
a person will like knowingly grab something not his. So will a
שבועה shvuah really help for such a person? So this is that's
the next question of the גמרא. Gemara. It says like this: וכי
ve-ki so the גמרא Gemara ואומר שלי הוא ונימא מיגו
דחשיד אממונא חשיד נמי אשבועתא. ve-omer sheli hu. Ve-neima migo de-chashid amamona,
chashid nami ashvuata.
If somebody is suspect for for monetary issues, for stealing, then they
should equally be suspect for swearing falsely, a שבועה shvuah won't help.
Again, we accept the idea that a שבועה shvuah sometimes does good
if a person is rationalizing, right? So oh I'll get money I'll
pay him back that's why I'm saying now I don't owe him,
right? So we've discussed already that if a person is rationalizing a
שבועה shvuah can help. But if a person in their own mind
knows that they're stealing, they're going to grab somebody's טלית, talit, okay,
what good is a שבועה shvuah going to help for such a
person? Shouldn't the fact that he's that he's suspect for doing such
an out and out act of stealing, shouldn't that make him suspect
for taking a false oath? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, לא
אמרינן מיגו דחשיד אממונא חשיד אשבועתא. lo amrinan migo de-chashid amamona chashid
ashvuata.
We don't say just because you're suspect for stealing you're going to
suspect for making a false שבועה. shvuah. Now what's the difference? So
תוספות Tosafot says, if we look at תוספות, Tosafot, דחשיד אממונא לא
חשיד אשבועתא, de-chashid amamona lo chashid ashvuata, תוספות Tosafot says, נראה דהיינו
טעמא משום דשבועה חמורה. nireh de-hainu ta'ama mishum de-shvuah chamura. A false
oath is very weighty. כידאיתא ביומא בשבועה שהעולם נזדעזע על לא תשא.
kide-ita be-Yoma be-shvuat she-ha-olam nizda-azei'a al lo tisa. When God said לא
תשא lo tisa את שם ה' אלהיך לשוא et shem Hashem Elokecha
la-shav
and the end of it is כי לא ינקה ה' את אשר
ישא את שמו לשוא. ki lo yenakeh Hashem et asher yisa et
shemo la-shav. God will not cleanse the person who takes his name
falsely. That's you know that is a very you know awe-inspiring, terror-inducing
type of a statement and the whole world shook, so people are
very afraid of a false שבועה. shvuah. Now you could more generalize
it right and say in general sadly sometimes people are much more
careful about ritual issues than they are about you know interpersonal and
ethical and monetary issues, right? So it could maybe be somebody won't
even eat like something without a הכשר hechsher even though they'll go
ahead and they'll steal money you know with somebody. They won't eat
you know 100 percent orange juice without a הכשר hechsher but they'll
go have no problem stealing money from someone else. But תוספות Tosafot
exactly. So תוספות Tosafot anyway so it could have been that type
of a statement which I think which I think also obviously has
truth to it, but תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* is particularly talking about the
weightiness of a שבועה shvua *shevuah* and therefore somebody could be a
גנב ganav *ganav*, but if you tell them they have to make
a שבועה shvua. *shevuah*, they'll admit. The other answer תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*
says is also interesting, which he says part of the point here
is, is
that maybe, you know, the שבועה shvua *shevuah* will stop you from
going through with what you're trying to do. You're making a false
claim and you're trying to steal, and the שבועה shvua *shevuah* will
stop you and you won't actually see it through. So when we
can get you still at like a decision point, you know, when
it hasn't, you haven't already committed to the act 100%, that might
do some good. Okay, whereas if you stole in the past, because
the question here is even if we say that if you're suspect
of money you're not going to swear falsely, let's say there's evidence,
there's proof that you have been a גזלן gazlan, *gazlan* in the
past, right? We had this yesterday, like the shepherd or whatever. If
there's evidence that somebody's been a גזלן gazlan. *gazlan* in the past,
we say they're not allowed to take a שבועה shvua *shevuah*. We
are afraid they'll swear falsely. So the other thing תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*
says is there might be a difference that a שבועה shvua *shevuah*
could stop you if you haven't yet committed 100%, right? So you,
because you have to take a שבועה shvua *shevuah*, you're going to...
maybe you'll change your mind, and then you will at the end
of the day not have been a גזלן gazlan? *gazlan*. But if
you actually have been already 100% of a גזלן gazlan *gazlan* in
the past, maybe then, you know, it's not... you can't be trusted.
The שבועה shvua *shevuah* will not do any good. All right, so
this is two interesting reasons why a שבועה shvua *shevuah* somebody could
be a גזלן gazlan, *gazlan* and a שבועה shvua *shevuah* make a
difference, either because generally people take a שבועה shvua *shevuah* more weightily
than they do גזילה *gezeilah*,
or because maybe we're talking specifically about somebody who hasn't yet fully
committed to being a גזלן gazlan. *gazlan*. All right, anyway, so that's
the point. Yes, it's possible you could go ahead and grab somebody's
טלית talis *tallis*, but if we tell you you have to make
a שבועה shvua *shevuah*, you'll back off. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, this is going to be the focus of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Do we say if you're suspect for stealing, a
שבועה shvua *shevuah* can still be effective? So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* continues. אי לאו תימא הכי *Ei lav teima hachi*, were you
not to say that, were you to say that a שבועה shvua,
*shevuah* won't be effective in such cases, האי דאמר רחמנא מודה במקצת
הטענה ישבע *Hai d'amar Rachmana modeh b'miktzas hatana yishava*, so the fact
the תורה *Torah* says that if you admit to part of a
debt you have to swear an oath? I say you owe me
a hundred, you say fifty, you have to take an oath. Why
does any שבועה shvua *shevuah* work? נימא מיגו דחשיד אממונא חשיד אשבועתא
naima migo d'chashid amamona chashid ashvuata? *Neima migo d'chashid amamona chashid ashuata*?
Why don't we say no, if you're lying and you're trying to
not to pay the other fifty, a שבועה shvua *shevuah* won't do
any good? So you see, even if you're suspect for trying to
steal, a שבועה shvua *shevuah* will do good. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says no, no, no, that's like we've said, that's because there's
a rationalizing that happens. התם אשתמוטי הוא hu, דקא משתמיט ליה *Hasam
ishtamuti hu d'ka mishtamit lei*. There you're just trying to buy time,
כדרבה *k'd'Rabba*. Like רבה *Rabba* says. Okay,
you know, and רבה *Rabba* says that the whole, you know, psychological
explanation of why a person is מודה במקצת *modeh b'miktzas*. He wants
to get out of all of it then, but he doesn't want,
he doesn't have the חוצפה *chutzpah* to deny it, so he really
wants to admit, but he needs time. Okay, so basically, normally maybe
a שבועה shvua *shevuah* won't do good, but in certain cases of
rationalizing they will. Okay, תדע *Teda*, you should know that's true, דאמר
רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב חסדא Rav Chisda הכופר במלוה כשר
kosher לעדות הכופר בפקדון פסול לעדות pasul le'edut? *d'amar Rav Idi bar
Avin amar Rav Chisda hakofair b'milveh kasher l'eidus hakofair b'pikadon pasul l'eidus*,
right? That if you deny a debt and you're proven to be
a liar, witnesses come, you're still a כשר עד *kasher eid*. Why
are you a כשר עד *kasher eid*? Why aren't you a גזלן
Gazlan, *gazlan*? You denied you owed the money, and it was proven
that you were lying. So it must be that denying a debt
does not... is not a real full act of גזילה *gezeilah*, because
maybe, or, you know, it might be halachically an act of גזילה
*gezeilah*, but in terms of what that does to you as a
person, are you really a גזלן gazlan *gazlan* who's and so on?
No, you're not, as you're not necessarily a רשע *rasha*. Maybe you're
planning on returning the money and you're just buying time. Okay, so
therefore, to say that a שבועה shvua, *shevuah* helps in some cases,
it might help in some cases where the person is rationalizing, is
not really intending to steal, just intending to buy time. But if
somebody knows that they're ממש *mamash* stealing, maybe a שבועה shvua *shevuah*
won't help in those cases.
אלא Ella, הא דתני רמי בר חמה *Ella ha d'tani Rami bar
Chama*,
so we're going to say, okay, but let's take a look. So
fine, I'll prove it to you from another place, from a case
of a פקדון pikadon *pikadon*. Because we just said if you're lying
about a פקדון pikadon *pikadon*, you are a גנב ganav. *ganav*. So
if that's true,
then a שבועה Shvua *shevuah* should never work if we think somebody
is lying about a פקדון pikadon *pikadon*, right? Because that means that
they're being a real גנב ganav, *ganav*. So if a שבועה Shvua
*shevuah* works in a case about a פקדון *pikadon*, if we're going
to make it, that shows that even somebody who's willing to be
a גנב ganav? *ganav*, a שבועה Shvua *shevuah* can still be helpful.
אלא הא דתני רמי בר חמה ארבעה שומרים צריכין כפירה במקצת והודיה
במקצת *Ella ha d'tani Rami bar Chama arba'ah shomrim tzrichin kfirah b'miktzas
v'hoda'ah b'miktzas*. We had this yesterday. Four שומרים *shomrim*, it's not enough
that you have to make an oath about what happened to the
object, you only make that oath if you're also a מודה במקצת
*modeh b'miktzas*. Okay, right? So I gave you three cows. I say
I gave you three. You say, "I know you didn't give me
three. You only gave me two." One of them I admit to,
and the other one something happened and I'm going to take a
שבועה Shvua *shevuah* that it was an אונס *oness*, I wasn't פושע
*poshea*, etc. So according to my claim, I gave you a cow
and you're saying that I never gave you that cow. The first
cow that we're talking about, right? So that's a case where it's
a פקדון *pikadon*, okay, and you're denying it. If you're really lying,
why are you taking a שבועה Shvua about it, right? Because if
you're really lying, then you're a straight up גזלן, gazlan? it's not
money, what rationalizing is there? If you have my cow and you're
not giving it back, you're a straight up גזלן. gazlan And so
if we think a שבועה Shvua can still help in that case
where there's no rationalizing, it shows you that even somebody who is
willingly going to steal and knowingly going to steal will still admit
if they're forced, might admit if they're forced to make a שבועה.
Shvua. Okay, so it says
נימא, neima, why don't we say מיגו דחשיד אממונא חשיד אשבועתא? migo
dechasheed amamona chasheed ashvuata? If you're suspect for stealing that first פיקדון,
pikadon, then the שבועה Shvua won't help. So you see that the
שבועה Shvua will help in those cases. So גמרא Gemara says no,
you know what, even in the case of a פיקדון pikadon there
could be a rationalizing. What's the rationalizing? השתא נמי אשתמוטי קא משתמיט,
hashtam nami ishtamutei ka mishtameit, he's just trying to buy time. סבר
משתכחנא לגנב, savar mishtachna leganav, you know what, maybe that cow is
not in your possession, maybe that cow was stolen or got lost.
So you're saying you don't have it because you're going to try
to find it. You're saying to yourself, I'll tell him I don't
have it and that'll buy me time, and therefore משתכחנא לגנב ואתפיסנא
ליה, mishtachna leganav ve'atfisleh leh, I'll find the גנב ganav, and then
I'll grab it back. Or אינמי משתכחנא ליה באגם ומייתינא ליה, inami
mishtachna leh ba'agam umasina leh, or I'll find it, it wandered off
into the swamp and I'll bring it back. So you don't want
to say that you were, it's funny, you'd rather say lie, right,
than say that you were negligent. But either way, okay, maybe I'll
you maybe that way I'll think that you forgot I gave it
to you and no, you know, I remembered you did give it
to me, I found it, here it is or whatever. Anyway, okay,
the point being that even though you have to take a שבועה
Shvua in a case of a פיקדון, pikadon, that doesn't prove that
we're suspect that you're a knowing גנב. ganav, Maybe if the only
issue possibility was you were a knowing גנב, ganav, maybe the שבועה
Shvua wouldn't do any good. But there's other possibilities as well, that
you're rationalizing, you're buying time and that's what the שבועה Shvua is
there for. Okay, yes.
Does אשתמוטי קא משתמיט ishtamutei ka mishtameit literally mean he pushes it
off?
No, it means that he's trying to so to get to remove
himself from the other person.
Like שמותי shamuti like רבי אלעזר שמותי?
Rabbi Elazar shamuti? No, no, that's with a תיו, tav, this is
a טית. tet. No,
it's לשמוט lashmit means like like it might be from שמיטה shmita
to release, but it means to remove himself from the other person's
grasp. Okay, so to extract himself or something. Okay, so גמרא Gemara
says אי
הכי הכופר בפיקדון אמאי פסול לעדות?
ey hachi
hakopher bepikadon amai pasul le'edut? So if that's true that even by
a case of פיקדון pikadon a person could be rationalizing and not
really stealing, so why if somebody is proven to have lied about
a פיקדון pikadon is he considered a גנב? ganav So and he's
פסול לעדות? pasul le'edut? נימא אשתמוטי קא משתמיט, neima ishtamutei ka mishtameit,
maybe even though he was lying about a פיקדון pikadon and proven
to be a liar, right, maybe he wasn't really a thief any
more than somebody who denies a debt is a thief, maybe he
was just buying time. סבר עד דבחשינא savar ad devachashna until I
search it out ומשתכחנא ליה umishtachna leh and I'll find it. So
so now that you're saying that there's a rationalizing going on and
that's why a שבועה Shvua will help, why if he's proven to
be a liar is he פסול לעדות? pasul le'edut? So גמרא Gemara
says no, כי אמרינן הכופר בפיקדון פסול לעדות, ki amrina hakopher bepikadon
pasul le'edut, when do we say that that type of a person
is פסול לעדות? pasul le'edut. כגון דאתו סהדי ואסהידו ביה, kegon de'atu
sahei ve'ashidu bei,
witnesses not only say that he was lying and they know that
he was given the פיקדון, pikadon, but they testify
דההיא שעתא de'ahi sha'ata that that moment that he was saying that
he didn't have it, so איתיה לפיקדון בביתיה, ito pikadon beveiteh, it
was there in his house, it was in his closet. So there's
no rationalizing, it's not like I gotta go ahead and it was
stolen, it was lost, I gotta find it. So we make you
make a שבועה shevua because we don't know, even if you're lying,
maybe it's in your closet and you're a real גנב, ganav maybe
it got lost and you're just rationalizing and buying time, so in
all cases you'll make a שבועה shevua even if a שבועה shavua
doesn't work when you're a knowing גנב, Ganav there's some cases where
you're rationalizing and a שבועה shavua will work. But if we can
prove that in a particular case you were a knowing גנב, Ganav,
it was in your house and you weren't giving it back, then
in that type of a case in the end of the day
you'll be פסול לעדות. But since we don't know what the facts
are we'll have you make a שבועה shavua because maybe you're just
rationalizing.
Okay, בבא ידא, bava yada, אינמי דהוה נקיט ליה בידיה inami dehavin
naktilei beyadei or what's in his house or was in his hand,
whatever, two variations. Fine. So now we're trying to argue is the
fact that we make a we know we make a שבועה, shavua
will a שבועה shavua work in the possibility that the guy in
his own mind is a knowing גנב Ganav, or knowing גזלן? gazlan.
Or is a שבועה shavua only going to work for cases where
the person has somehow rationalized that they're actually a good guy and
what they're doing is not so bad. But if they know that
they're a גזלן it won't do any good, that's the question. Okay,
and all of this gets back to רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan claim
that the purpose of the שבועה shavua is to stop somebody from
just going in and grabbing somebody's shirt off their back because if
that's what we're afraid of, a person who would grab somebody's shirt
off their back is a knows that they're a גנב ganav. right
or גזלן, knows that there's a גזלן. So to say that a
שבועה shvua. will work in that case says מיגו דחשיד אממונא, migo
dechasheed amamona, just because you're suspect of doing some of an act
of like stealing money doesn't necessarily mean you'll make a false שבועה,
shvua, שבועה shvua. could still be effective in such a case. You
want to add something, Dan, or you're good? Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אלא הא דאמר רב הונא, Ella had'amar Rav
Huna, so that's where we're still going to try to prove whether
a שבועה shvua will work in such a case. Okay.
That's what רב הונא Rav Huna says, משביעין אותו שבועה שאינה ברשותו.
Mashbi'inoso shvua she'eina birshuto. Okay, you come and you basically,
let me just check רש"י Rashi for a second.
Right. So I, David, I gave you my cow to watch and
you said an accident occurred and I'm willing to pay you though.
Here it is, ten thousand, two thousand dollars for your cow. And
I say, I still need you to make an oath to me
that you're not holding on to it. I know you have an
eye on my cow. So even if you're willing to pay, it's
like, man, it is not a good deal to be a שומר,
Shomer, right? You're going to have to make שבועות Shvuos all the
time, like I hope you're compensating my שומר Shomer well. Anyway, so
he's willing to pay me and I still have to make a
שבועה shvua according to רב נחמן Rav Nachman that he's not lying
and keeping it to himself. All right. Now, if that's true, right,
so presumably we're afraid that he's just a גנב ganav. if he's
willing to pay me, he said something happened to it or whatever.
Now, so why don't we say חשיד אממונא חשיד אשבועתא? chashid amamona
chashid ashvuata? The funny thing is he could be saying, well, what
do you mean,
I'm not a גנב, ganav, I'm buying it from you.
Right, so that's the question: what איסור Issur is it to take
something against my will and pay me for it? So we're going
to see that's according to חז"ל Chazal the איסור Issur of לא
תחמוד. Lo Tachmod. לא תחמוד Lo Tachmod they understand to mean, right,
well, right, is to basically, right, is to take something against my
will even if you're paying for it. So right. So now you
could say maybe that's not the same degree of חשד אממונא. Chashad
amamona. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara understands that as חשד אממונא Chashad
amamona meaning sort of like any monetary transgression. But we'll see exactly
what let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says,
נימא, Naima, that רב הונא Rav Huna says, excuse me, משביעין אותו
שבועה שאינה ברשותו, Mashbi'inoso shvua she'eina birshuto, נימא מיגו דחשיד אממונא חשיד
אשבועתא? naima migo dechasid amamona chasid ashavuasa, You know, if we're afraid
that it's still there, meaning if it really was lost or stolen
then it's true what you're
saying, you're paying. So to think that you know that it's not
lost and you're keeping it to yourself and you're paying for it,
if I really suspect you about that, why would you make then
you're חשיד אממונא, chashid amamona, then you're doing a knowingly doing a
monetary sin. How will a שבועה shvua help? So the גמרא Gemara.
says so it shows you that a שבועה shvua will help in
that case. So the גמרא Gemara says no, התם נמי מורה ואמר
דמי קא יהיבנא ליה. Hacham nami moreh v'amar dmei ka yahivna lei.
There too you rationalize and you say 'I'm paying for it'. Is
that really stealing? You know, as long as you're paying for it
you feel... oh, but now you have to make a... so again,
if there's any type of rationalizing, I think I said this before,
it's such a good מוסר Mussar right before ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
you know, like they've done these studies, right, that people basically at
the end of the day so many people operate not based on
like some abstract moral code, but like whether they can still think
of themselves as a good person. You know, like so they I
think I've said this before, they did a study like in a
workplace, they leave like a bottle of soda on a table in
a common room, nobody has a problem taking it for themselves. You
leave a dollar there, nobody will take it. Okay, because you know
soda you can rationalize, a dollar's
like that's stealing.
Okay, so you know, so it's really like here it goes, you
can rationalize it, a שבועה shvua will help because you still want
to think of yourself as a good person, so you're not going
to take a שבועה shvua that you're going to know is going
to be a false שבועה. shvua Okay, so that's one then. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara says that, okay, yes, is that person
doing an עבירה? Aveira? Absolutely. But they can rationalize and that's why
a שבועה shvua will be helpful. התם נמי מורה ואמר דמי קא
יהיבנא ליה. Hacham nami moreh v'amar dmei ka yahivna lei. אמר ליה
רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא והא קעבר על לא תחמוד. Amar lei Rav
Acha miDifti l'Ravina v'ha ka'avar al Lo Tachmod.
It's very nice that you can rationalize, but you're directly transgressing a
biblical prohibition of coveting. And coveting is not the same as stealing;
coveting is
understood by חז"ל Chazal to mean that you possess it and even
if you're willing to pay for it that the person did not
want to give up. So why aren't you aware that you're a
knowing transgressor and that so therefore why will a שבועה shvua help
in that case? So he says no, לא תחמוד לאינשי בלא דמי
משמע להו. Lo Tachmod l'inshei b'lo dmei mashma lehu. People don't think
that לא תחמוד Lo Tachmod means if I don't pay. They think,
even though it's not true, לא תחמוד Lo Tachmod means even if
you do pay, they think that they're not really transgressing if they
pay. So since people rationalize and think they're not really transgressing if
they pay for it, for that type of a person a שבועה
shvua will work. But if you in your own mind know that
you're a transgressor, you're a גנב, ganav you're a גזלן, whatever, in
that type of a case maybe a שבועה shvua will not work.
Yes, Charlie? One minute, Charlie had his hand up.
Yeah. So one of the questions we had was why is this
פרק perek coming before the second פרק perek where they talk about
lost items? This issue of rationalization, lost items is something that you
actually have to guard against when we're actually finding a lost item.
That could be true. Yeah, Dov, what do you want to say?
So in other words, in this case, the cow is in the
closet, the guy's rationalizing to himself and saying 'I'm really paying for
it so I'm not a thief', so if we make him take
a שבועה shvua he'll confess?
Yeah, because the שבועה shvua, you'd have to out-and-out in the name
of God, you would have to say the cow isn't in my
closet. There's no way you can rationalize whether what I'm doing is
really considered stealing, I can make a whole story in my head.
But if I have to directly take an... oath in the name
of God that the cow is not in my closet, right,
you'll fall away in the face of that.
No, because there's no way I can rationalize that. Right. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara, says okay ואלא הא דאמר רב נחמן משביעין אותו
שבועת היסת, ve'ela ha de'amar Rav Nachman mashbin oso shevuas heses, that
which רב נחמן Rav Nachman says you make him take a false
excuse me you make him take a... if somebody just completely denies
you owe me a hundred dollars no I don't. So even a
כופר הכל kofer hakol rabbinically you have to make a שבועת היסת.
shevuas heses. So we assume that a
כופר הכל kofer hakol can't rationalize of course we know that they
can because we just said like I'm trying to find the money
or whatever but תוספות Tosafot says maybe רב נחמן Rav Nachman even
includes a case of a פקדון anyway it's not exactly clear what
the question is because we seem to have addressed it.
נימא מיגו דחשיד אממונא חשיד אשבועתא, naima migo dechasid amamona chasid ashavuasa.
why don't we say if we just make you make a שבועה
shvua in all cases you know you should be why don't we
say that you know you're if you're suspect for stealing you won't
you'll take a false oath. That question is not so clear because
we just got through saying that somebody could have a loan and
could have a פקדון and they could be lying and wait trying
to find it and to you know and so on and still
rationalizing in that case. But let's look at the next case. ותו
הא דתני ר' חייא שנים נשבעים ונוטלים
מבעל הבית, vesu ha desani Rabbi Chiyya shnayim nishba'im venotlim miba'al habayis,
remember that case that we'd introduced right I tell the store owner
to feed my workers and then at the end of the day
the store owner says I fed them and the workers say he
didn't feed us and they both take an oath and I pay
both of them so one of them is lying. Now there's very
little rationalizing going on
here right if the store owner did not feed my workers and
he's lying he's out and out stealing from me. If the workers
were fed and they're lying and they want me to pay them
again they're out and out stealing from me, right, there's no rationalizing.
I guess you could always imagine that workers feel they're being underpaid
and they rationalize it that way okay
what for the sake of a meal.
Right, but it seems here if you're going to make you take
somebody take an oath to collect from me there's very little rationalizing
that could be going on and nevertheless what good is the oath
going to do if they're willing to actually steal money from me?
Okay so שנים נשבעים ונוטלים מבעל הבית shnayim nishba'im venotlim miba'al habayis
נימא naima מיגו דחשיד אממונא חשיד אשבועתא. migo dechasid amamona chasid ashavuasa
If they're really willing to take money from me what good is
the oath going to do? ותו הא דאמר רב ששת vesu ha
de'amar Rav Sheshes what רב ששת Rav Sheshes says שלוש שבועות משביעין
אותו shalosh shevuos mashbin oso you make a normal שומר shomer who
says that you know whatever the object got stolen it wasn't my
fault he has to take three שבועות. shevuos. What are the three
שבועות? shevuos? Number one שלא פשעתי בה shelo pashati bah I wasn't
negligent okay that would be the classic thing it got lost not
due by negligence. Number two שבועה שלא שלחתי בה יד shevua shelo
shalachsi bah yad I did not use it for myself. If during
the time I was supposed to be watching it I made use
of it for my own purposes then I become liable for anything
that happens even if I'm not negligent okay so you go ahead
and you lend me I don't know a blanket not lend me
you have me watch a blanket and one day I decide to
use the blanket you know as I'm curling up and watching TV
and then I fold it up and I whatever and I'm done
using it at from that point on I'm liable for anything that
happens even if I'm not negligent even if it gets stolen afterwards
you know now there might be ways in which I could somehow
reverse it and completely restore it to its previous state but whatever
there's a case where if I'm שליח יד shaleiach yad it doesn't
matter if I wasn't negligent. Okay שבועה שאינה ברשותי shevua she'eina birshusi
and
the third one is I have to say it's not hidden in
my closet because it could be true I'm not negligent and I
didn't use it but nothing happened to it it's still hidden in
my closet I'm planning to keep it. Okay so you have to
make all those three שבועות. shevuos. So the question is again the
last one the שבועה shvua. that it's not hidden in my closet.
נימא why don't we
say מיגו דחשיד אממונא חשיד chasid אשבועתא ashavuasa since you're חשיד chasid
for ממונא mamona you're חשיד אשבועתא because similar to the point before
if it is in your closet right why aren't you giving it
back? So must be that you're planning just on stealing it and
taking it for yourself so then you're like a known
גנב. ganav Okay so that's different than before because before I was
willing to pay so I rationalized yes I'm keeping it but it's
not so bad I'm paying for it. Here I'm basically claiming that
you know it got stolen or lost or whatever and I'm not
paying and really it's just in my closet. Okay so this is
a case where clearly we're making you take a שבועה shvua. that
you are not misappropriating a פקדון that is in your closet and
you're keeping it for yourself. So if you're really doing that how
is the שבועה shvuah going to do any good? Why don't we
say that if you're a knowing thief a שבועה shvuah won't do
any good. אלא אמר גמרא לא אמרינן מיגו דחשיד אממונא חשיד אשבועתא.
ela amar Gemara lo amrinan migo dechasid amamona chasid ashavuasa. This
is a very important principle for all הלכות halachos of שבועות shevuos
which is you do not need to say the person is rationalizing
to say a שבועה shvuah, will do will do good. Even if
the person does not rationalize people will be willing to steal and
not willing to take a false oath and a שבועה shvuah, actually
will do good and therefore when רב נחמן Rav Nachman says the
reason that the guy who grabs the טלית tallis has to make
a שבועה shvuah is because he might be a knowing thief and
to prevent people from grabbing טליתות talisos off of people's back yes
somebody could be a knowing thief and a שבועה shvuah will make
the person back off. Okay so that's very good clear position of
the גמרא. Gemara אביי אמר Abaye amar now אביי Abaye says, not
necessarily. Maybe there are times where maybe there's a generic rationalizing
that can always happen. In principle, if in your own mind you're
a thief, you'll be willing to take a false שבועה. shvuah But
in all many, many cases you can rationalize. What type of rationalizing
will you have? Here's the rationalizing: חיישינן שמא מלוה ישנה יש לו
עליו. chaishinan shema milva yeshana yesh lo alav.
So let's say so says we're afraid that the guy, this might
be why the guy will grab the טלית tallis and this will
be why even in these cases we mentioned before, a person will
be able to not in their own mind think they're a גנב.
ganav Why? Because like I said by the state workers. Yeah, he
underpays us. You know, I see David walking around with his nice
coat and I think, you know, David owes me a hundred bucks
from ten years ago. He doesn't remember, there's no way I'm going
to prove it. I'm just going to grab it off his back.
I always can have some reason why this person owes me the
money and I'm entitled to his object. Okay? So that's why a
שבועה, shvuah. it's almost arguing more in theory with the previous position
rather than in principle. If somebody really in their own mind knew
they were a גנב, ganav they'd take a false שבועה. shvuah But
pretty much any case you can dream up, a person can dream
up a rationalization. Okay? A person can always say, yeah, guy really
owes me money from a long time ago and that's why I'm
entitled to it. And that's why a שבועה shevuah, will do good,
okay, because it will break but because there's always some rationalization going
on. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. ולא אמינא, velo amina,
okay, the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ee hachi says the גמרא,
Gemara חיישינן שמא מלוה ישנה יש לו עליו. chaishinan shema milva yeshana
yesh lo alav. אי הכי נשקליה בלא שבועה. ee hachi nishkaley belo
shvua.
So if that's true, if we basically say like
look,
if the guy didn't have money owed to him he wouldn't even
then then the שבועה wouldn't do any good because he'd be a
knowing גנב ganav in his own mind, you know he'd be a
knowing גנב and a שבועה wouldn't help. The reason a שבועה is
going to do good is because he's he's not a גנב in
his own mind because he because he thinks the guy owes him
money. So if he thinks the guy owes him money, what good
is the שבועה going to do? The שבועה is going to do,
take a שבועה the טלית tallis is yours. Fine, I'll take a
שבועה the טלית tallis is mine. And take the שבועה that the
טלית tallis is yours. Fine, I'll take a שבועה the טלית tallis,
is mine, it is mine, it's payment for a debt. Right? So
what good if you if the rationalization is the guy really owes
this to me, he's convinced himself right that the guy really owes
this to me. It's opposed to the previous case. The previous case
is I know I'm lying when I say I don't I don't
owe you money, but I'm trying to you know get the money
together. So if I have to take an oath I don't owe
you money, I won't take that because that's a lie. I know
it's a lie, okay, I'm just not a גנב because I'm trying
to get the money together. In this case, if I think he
owed me money and that's how I rationalized it, then I'll take
an oath that it's mine, and this is mine, it's payment of
a debt. So the גמרא Gemara says נשקליה בלא שבועה. nishkaley belo
shvua. So what good is a שבועה going to do, let him
just take it. So the גמרא Gemara. says no. אלא חיישינן שמא
ספק מלוה ישנה יש לו עליו. ela chaishinan shema safek milva yeshana
yesh lo alav. No no no, because I don't know for sure
you owe me money. I see your nice coat, cloak on you
or coat on you
and I think you know I think he owes me some money.
I have a vague recollection that he owes me some money, he
hasn't paid me. So in that case, if I have to take
an oath that it's mine, I won't take an oath that it's
mine because I don't know for sure it's mine. Okay so the
גמרא Gemara says one minute.
ולא אמינא תפס ממונא מספק משתבע נמי מספק? velo amina tafas mamona
misafek mishtava nami misafek? But one minute, if I'm going to grab
the coat because you might owe me money and that's enough for
me to rationalize, why won't I take a שבועה that it's my
coat because in my mind it it might really be my coat.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי פרישי
אינשי מספק שבועה ולא פרישי מספק ממונא. amar Rav Sheshet brei de-Rav
Idi parishi inish misafek shvua velo parishi misafek mamona. I will not
do something that might be a false oath, but I will do
something that might not really be my money and I'll take it
anyway. Why? מאי טעמא ממונא איתא בחזרה שבועה ליתא בחזרה. mai taama
mamona isha behazara shvua leita behazara. If the money, I can always
have remorse, I can always remember more precisely and give it back
to you if I got it wrong. But a שבועה, once I've
made a false שבועה I can't reverse the fact that I made
a false שבועה. So something that might not that doesn't have a
good הכשר, hechsher, that might not be כשר whatever, that I won't
eat because if I've eaten טריף treif I can't make that go
back. But if money, maybe maybe not whatever, I'll explain to myself
why it's okay for me to take it. If whatever, if I
ever feel different about it, I'll always just give the money back.
All right, so it's a such a great גמרא Gemara right before
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah about how about how well we rationalize to
ourselves all types of things and particularly in the בין אדם לחבירו
bein adam le-chavero realm, right? You know, in the ritual realm, oh
then it's already a violation, I can't change that, that's you know
a done deal, that's between me and G-d. But somehow we give
ourselves a lot of latitude here. So in theory there's not a
big difference between, I mean תוספות Tosafot starts to figure out a
case where there's a difference, but there's not a big difference between
these two approaches. One approach is
even when people won't rationalize, somebody can in their mind know they're
a גנב and they still won't do a you know you know
won't make a false שבועה. And the other which is... אביי Abaye
with which is maybe even a little bit more disturbing is that
people will always find a way to rationalize so that a שבועה
maybe שבועה really only only helps so people rationalize, but people will
almost always find a way to rationalize. So in the end of
the day there's not a big difference. They agree that שבועות shvuos
can cover almost all cases. אביי Abaye is just willing to say
that people will rationalize in almost any case. Yes.
Teacher, I read some מוסר mussar also a little bit differently. You
can't take words back. Some type of action I can rectify, but
I can't take words back. Aha. I can tell you that.
Oh you mean like like don't say certain things, like you get
into a fight and you say things that you should never have
said then you can't take those. That's very powerful.
For something that I said
even at the interpersonal level. That's an excellent point.
Okay. Yes.
Suppose they take a שבועה, like they're looking for the cow, you
take the שבועה, and then you then you actually do find the
cow, you want to restore, but you already took the שבועה that.
Well we hope that, you mean you're saying once you've taken the
שבועה then that might close off a certain avenue of fessing up?
It's true, but you know we can only do so much, I
mean that's sort of like a תקנת השבים takanas hashavim issue. But
you can only do so much, you know, the case comes to
us in court, we're going to try to use whatever devices are
at our, you know, disposal to get, you know, to get people
to be, you know, to get the facts on the, you know,
you know, on the table. Okay. Now we have a, now that
we're talking about the case of two people arguing about the טלית,
tallis right? So we discussed what type of a שבועה you make,
how you frame it. We discussed the purpose of the שבועה. Is
it to clarify the facts? Is it to be more preventative? How
a שבועה breaks through certain rationalizing, you know, and so on. Now
we're going to go on with the scenario of the two people
holding onto a טלית tallis and introduce a variation on that scenario
which leads to fascinating discussions in the גמרא. Gemara Let's take a
look. Okay. בעי רמי בר חמא... Ba'ei Rami bar Chama... no, בעי
רבי זירא. Ba'ei Rabbi Zeira. So רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira asks: תקפה
אחד בפנינו מהו? Takpah echad befanenu mahu? So here David and I
are grabbing onto the טלית tallis and we come to בית דין
Beis Din and we're each holding on, and then I yank it
out of David's hand. And they saw me yank it out of
David's hand. Does he still get half, or do I because now
I'm holding all of it, I get it all? Okay. So what's
the story?
היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי דשתיק, Ei deshatik, if
David as I yanked it out of his hand didn't say anything,
remained silent, אודויי אודי ליה, oduyei odei lei, he's implicitly conceding that
it's mine. Okay. ואי דקצווח, Ve'ei dekatzavach, and if he's yelling, "Hey,
you took that out of my hand, give it back!" מאי הוה
ליה למעבד? mai havah lei lema'avad? What should he have done? Just
because he's, I'm stronger than he is, that means that like you
know that I now, it's now I now win the case? בית
דין Beis Din saw that we were both holding on to it.
So the facts as registered by the בית דין Beis Din is
that we both had a חזקה. chazakah. So now how's it any
different than than me putting my hand in his pocket and taking
my, you know, a wallet out of his pocket? That that doesn't
make me מוחזק. muchzak. They saw me grab it out of his
hand, big deal.
So, לא צריכה דשתיק מעיקרא והדר צווח. Lo tzricha deshatik me'ikara vehadar
tzavach. First David didn't say anything and then he started yelling. You
know, he said, so so first I grabbed it out of his
hand, he wasn't, and then ten minutes later he said, "Hey, didn't
you see, he took it out of my hand?" So מה? mah?
What do we say? מדשתיק אודויי אודי ליה. Midshatik oduyei odei lei.
Since initially he was silent, do we say that he was implicitly
conceding that it's mine? או דילמא כיון דקצווח השתא, O dilma keivan
dekatzavach hashta,
since now he's yelling, איגלאי מילתא, iglay milsa, now it makes it
clear
retroactively דהאי דשתיק מעיקרא, dehai deshatik me'ikara, why was he silent initially?
סבר הא חזו לי רבנן, Savar ha chazu lei rabanan, because the
rabbis saw what I what happened. Why do I have to yell?
It happened right in their presence, they saw him grab it out
of my hand. Now read this way, it seems like it's a
total question of like psychology. What do we infer from his silence
and then his yelling? As the גמרא Gemara is going to continue,
it seems like it's going to move away from that question about
how do we sort of like read the tea leaves, how do
we read his silence, and seems like it'll be a bigger question.
But anyway, that's how it's framing the question now. Yes.
You're telling me these two people walk to בית דין Beis Din
holding on to a טלית tallis and things go into an entire
court case, but those both of them don't like take the טלית
tallis and put it somewhere and say like?
Right, I guess the question, I guess at some point they do,
but we haven't like gotten to that case yet, you know?
They're in front of a בית דין Beis Din and they're seeing
it happen.
Right. I mean, you're right, like in general you imagine that what
happens is that if we were grabbing onto a טלית tallis and
witnesses saw us grabbing it, I'm saying it's mine and you're saying
it's yours and witnesses see, and then you grab it out of
my hand and then we come to the בית דין, Beis Din,
you just you just get the witnesses to say this is what
we saw, and anything sort of after that.
Right, but you're both still holding it on, say okay. Right,
right.
So witnesses or a wall. Right. So presumably that we would get
to that stage, but we haven't done that yet, you know?
What about three guys on the street?
Yeah, or two guys. Like why, yeah that's, meaning that's the point,
like why do you have to have it in front of the
בית דין? Beis Din? Meaning like you would sort of say like,
you know, if witnesses came and said we saw the two of
them holding onto a טלית tallis and then one of them got
stronger and yanked it out of the hand of the other, we
would say okay, but if initially they were both holding on, so
we should presume that that's the case. Right, so I guess you
could have framed it.
But he's presuming that they חזו ליה
רבנן.
chazu
lei rabanan.
Right, I know, I know, it is, I agree, it's strange that
they. see this taking place. That's a בפנינו. befaneinu. You know, the
more normal thing is witnesses saw it and what's happening is not
that they're walking in front of a בית דין beis din holding
on, but that the witnesses once the witnesses see, but the point
is but if at that stage it was clear like you agreed
to okay we're going to give it over and then we're going
to go, then there's no question, but anyway, it's a funny let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. Okay, but yes, it
is a strange scenario.
Okay, אמר רב נחמן תא שמע, Amar Rav Nachman, ta shma, we
have a ברייתא braisa that says when is this true that if
they're both holding on to it you split it? ששניהם אדוקים בה,
she-shneihem adukin bah, when they're both holding tightly on to it or
equally on to it. אבל היתה טלית יוצאת מתחת ידו של אחד
מהם, Aval hayta tallis yotzes mitachas yado shel echad meihem, if one
of them was holding on and the other was saying no no
he took it from me it's mine it's mine, המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah.
So then the other guy has the burden of proof. So the
גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי נימא
כדקתני, Ei neima kedikatni, if it's like what the ברייתא braisa says
simply, one guy is holding and another guy is yelling it's mine,
פשיטא, peshita, of course, that's the strong halacha. I'm holding on to
my shirt and somebody else is yelling it's mine it's mine, of
course he's not believed. אלא, so the scenario that the ברייתא braisa
has to tell us that if I'm holding on to it the
other guy isn't believed must be שתקף אחד בפנינו, she-takaf echad bifaneinu,
that we were both initially holding on to it, but if now
I'm the only one holding on to it, then we would say
that maybe I would be believed, maybe and maybe that's the case
of the ברייתא braisa and that's the case of המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, as long as now I am holding
on to it. Now by the way to just step back a
bit because you know notice here like we haven't said initially he
was שתק shatak and then he was and then he
yelled and what does it show about your silence, maybe it's really
sort of saying in this type of a case where there's no
real evidence and it's all about grabbing it and nobody can prove
it, you know, why because we took the snapshot at the moment
we saw them both holding on to it, does that mean that
they're equally מוחזק? muchzak? If we took the snapshot a little bit
later after they continue fighting and one guy is holding on to
it, maybe that means give the מוחזק, muchzak, you know, which I
know is strange like you know המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero
alav hara'ayah, but so what, just the fact that you were able
to grab onto it earlier in the fight why should that mean
that it's yours, you know? So anyway so it's possible that the
גמרא Gemara really besides the reframing really does think that in a
case like this where nobody has any evidence or whatever, you know,
maybe again maybe if it was known that this had been my
shirt from beforehand like it would be different, but in a case
where it's a lost object, it's a מציאה, metzia, we know neither
came with any particular stake or rights. Who knows? Maybe we let
the fight continue and we see where we are when it finally
comes to the בית דין. beis din. Anyway so that's what the
גמרא Gemara wants to say. It says so why do we say
that this ברייתא braisa means that one guy grabbed it and then
the other guy is
מוציא מחברו? motzi mechavero? So so אלא שתקף אחד בפנינו, Ella she-takaf
echad bifaneinu, so you see it seems to be that תקפה takfa
does work. גמרא Gemara says לא, Lo, not necessarily.
הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאתו לקמן כי תפסי לה תרוייהו. Hacha b'mai
askinan k'gon d'asoh l'kaman ki tafsei lah tavrayhu. No, no, no, it's
a different case. They both were holding on to it. ואמרינן להו
זילו פלגו, Va-amrinan le-hu zilu palgu, go divide, go split it, okay?
Now again going back to your case we say what we just
trust them to divide it, we don't sort of like take charge
of the situation? It sounds like we say okay here's the הלכה,
halacha, go split it, goodbye. And then we trust them to go
take care of it, okay? ונפקו, V'nafku, then they left the court.
והדר אתו, V'hadar asu, and then they came back. כי תפיס לה
חד מינייהו, ki tefis lah chad mineihu, one of them was holding
on to it. האי אמר אודויי אודי לי, Hai amar oduyei odi
li, he says yeah after we left the court the other guy
conceded it to me that it was mine. והאי אמר, V'hai amar,
and the other says no, בדמי אגרתיה ניהליה, bedmei agartieh nihleih, after
we left the court you told us to split it, I said
I'll sell you my half and he said yes and he took
it and now he's not paying me for it. דאמרינן ליה, De-amrinan
leih, so then we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'ayah. דאמרינן ליה, De-amrinan leih, we say to the guy who's not
holding onto it, עד השתא חשדת ליה בגזלן, ad hashta chashadat lei
b'gazlan,
until this point you were claiming he was a thief, והשתא מוגרת
ליה בלא סהדי, v'hashta mograt lei b'lo sahadi,
now you're selling it to him without witnesses? So if he's holding
on to it now presumably that means somehow you conceded, you gave
it, okay? If you you would not have sold it to him
without having gotten some written proof at that stage that he owed
you the money. Okay so that would be a המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah in terms of what how we interpret
what happens afterwards. Okay but that doesn't prove our case where in
our presence one guy just yanks it out of the other guy's
hand. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'is eima, if you want I can say
כדקתני דאתו לקמן כי תפסי לה חד מינייהו. kedikatni de-asoh l'kaman ki
tafsei lah chad mineihu. No, no, no, it is like it says
that they they... First we saw it one was holding on, so
what's the חידוש? chiddush? So the חידוש chiddush is ואידך מצריך בסרוכי.
ve'idach mitzrich basseru'ei. The other guy is just holding on to like
the tassels, to the
threads, right, to the fringes, okay? ואפילו ve'afilu just to tell you
that that is not considered really holding on. ואפילו לסומכוס דאמר ממון
המוטל בספק חולקין בלא שבועה, ve'afilu lesumchos de'amar mamon hamutal besafek cholkin
belo shevuah, even סומכוס Sumchos who is very ready to split anything
that is debated and even split it without a שבועה, מודה סומכוס
modeh Sumchos in this case he would admit דסירכא לאו כלום היא,
desircha lav klum hi, that just like this holding on by the
edge, or by the threads, that's nothing. Now I don't exactly know
what is the limit definition of the סירכא, sircha, right? Like what
does it mean? Like I mean we could have a big טלית
tallis and I could be holding on to the edge of it
and having a very firm grip. What, I have to have my
hands around the midsection of it? It seems like that this is
like the tassels of the טלית tallis and it's not the actual
garment itself. You could hold on to the edge, but if you're
holding on to just the fringes, that's a different story. Anyway, not
exactly clear why that should be a different story. I mean, why,
it's conceptually not considered the טלית tallis itself? It's considered just like
something, I guess that's why we call it the fringes, because it's
not the טלית tallis, itself. All right, anyway, we still don't have
any answer.
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to move on. אם תימצי לומר,
im timtzi lomar, were you to say, תקף אחד בפנינו מוציאין אותה
מידו, takaf echad befanenu motzi'in otah miyado, if a guy yanked it
out of the other guy's hands, we would say give it back,
that doesn't mean anything, you're both equally מוחזק. muchzak. Then דהקדש אינה
מקודשת. dehekdesh einah mekudeshet.
So ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are fighting over it. If ראובן
Reuven were to yank it out of שמעון's Shimon hands, we would
say that doesn't prove anything, we see that you're both holding on.
So similarly if ראובן Reuven says, I מקדיש makdish the טלית, tallis
then that's meaningless. If he would grab the טלית tallis, it's meaningless,
being מקדיש makdish it's meaningless. He can't מקדיש makdish something that שמעון
Shimon is מוחזק muchzak in. Okay, but אם תימצי לומר תקף אחד
בפנינו אין מוציאין אותה מידו, im timtzi lomar takaf echad befanenu ein
motzi'in otah miyado,
but if ראובן Reuven yanked it out of שמעון's Shimon hands, we
would say, okay, now ראובן Reuven is fully מוחזק, muchzak, it's all
ראובן's, Reuven either because somehow might makes right or what the גמרא
Gemara seemed to be saying before, we interpret שמעון's Shimon silence, initial
silence, as if שמעון Shimon was conceding. So if that's true, what
if he didn't physically yank it out of his hands, but הקדישה
בלא תקף מהו? hikdishah belo takaf mahu? What if he was מקדיש
makdish it without physically yanking it out of his hands? Okay, so
whereas whereas if he yanked it out of your hands, your silence
would be a concession, let's say I say, I מקדיש makdish the
whole טלית, tallis and you don't say anything while
we're both holding it.
Well, while we're both holding it, but you don't say anything. So
is your silence a concession? You let me be מקדיש makdish the
whole thing without saying anything. So the same way if you let
me yank it without saying anything you're conceding, if I מקדיש makdish
the whole thing without saying it you're conceding. Or do we say,
why do I have to say something? He's מקדיש makdish something that
I'm holding on to. I have no need to say anything. Okay,
so what do we say, מהו? mahu? כיון דאמר מר אמירתו לגבוה
כמסירתו להדיוט דמי, keivan de'amar mar amirato legavo'ah kimesirato lhediot dami, since
we normally say
verbally giving something to הקדש hekdesh is like physically handing it over
to another person, כמאן דתקפה דמי, keman detakfah dami,
so verbally being מקדיש makdish it should have the same impact as
physically yanking it out of the guy's hands. Okay, it's like I'm
physically handing it to הקדש, hekdesh, that's the power of my words,
and therefore your silence is a concession. או דילמא, o dilma, or
do we say, השתא מיהא הלא תקפה, hashta miha halo takfah, I
have not yet yanked it out, you're still holding it on, and
my words don't mean anything if it's in your possession. וכתיב איש
כי יקדיש את ביתו קדש, uchetiv ish ki yakdish et beito kodesh,
if a man sanctifies his house, מה ביתו
ברשותו, mah beito bireshuto, the same way your house has to be
in your
possession, אף כל ברשותו, af kol bireshuto, anything in your possession, לאפוקי
האי דלאו ברשותו, le'afokei hai delav bireshuto, this isn't. So you can
say, if you physically yank it from me I'm going to say
something, you're trying to take it away from me. But if you
say words, those words don't mean anything while I'm physically holding it.
While I'm physically holding it it's under my control and my possession,
so why should I say anything? And therefore I had no need
and my silence doesn't mean anything. Okay, so that's the question. So
again, it seems at this stage that it's all a question of
psychology. How do we interpret your silence in the face of yanking
or in the face of saying that I'm מקדיש makdish it? But
now where the גמרא's Gemara going to go to, it's very hard
to continue seeing the conversation to be one of psychology. Okay, let's
take a look. תא שמע. ta shema.
דההוא מסותא, dehahu mesuta, a certain bathhouse, דהוו מנצו עליה בי תרי,
dehavu mintzu aleih bei terei, two people were fighting over it. Okay,
and that's a case where neither are מוחזק, muchzak, right, because it's
like a bathhouse or whatever. האי אמר דידי הוא, hai amar didi
hu, one says it's mine, והאי אמר דידי הוא, vehai amar didi
hu, this one says it's mine. קם חד מינייהו ואקדשה. kam chad
mineihu ve'akdeshah. So one guy got up and said, if that's the
way it's going to be, fine, I מקדיש makdish it all to
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, I can't have my way, I'm
just going to be מקדיש makdish it. פרשי מינה רבי חנינא ורבי
אושעיא וכולהו רבנן. parshi mineh Rabbi Chanina veRabbi Oshaya vechulhu rabbanan. So
רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya and all the rabbis
stopped using the bathhouse because they figured it's now הקדש, hekdesh, or
they have to be concerned it might be הקדש, hekdesh, right? And
they're using something that belongs to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
אמר ליה רבי אושעיא לרבא, amar leh Rabbi Oshaya leRabba, רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya said to רבא, Rabba, כי אזלת קמיה דרב חסדא לכפרי,
ki azlat kamei deRav Chisda leKafri, when you go see רב חסדא
who happens to be in כפרי, Kafri, בעי. ba'ei. ask him what
the הלכה halacha is with this bathhouse because you know we need
to use the bathhouse.
So כי אתא לסורא ki ata l'Sura so he was going to
Kafri but he was passing through Sura and אמר ליה רב המנונא
amar lei Rav Hamnuna so Rav Hamnuna who was in Sura so
you know he passed through he saw Rav Hamnuna there he figured
he'd ask him while he was on the way to go find
Rav Chisda. רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna said to him מתניתין היא. matnisin
hi. We can learn the הלכה halacha from a משנה. mishna. What
משנה? mishna? Not our משנה, mishna, a משנה mishna in טהרות. Taharos.
I can't believe none of you thought about quoting this משנה mishna
in טהרות. Taharos. ספק בכורות. Sfeik Bechoros. So if you have an
animal that is a ספק בכור. safek bechor. What's the case of
a ספק בכור? safek bechor? Your cow gives birth and you don't
know if your cow had given birth earlier or not.
Or what would be two where you don't know if it was
a twin.
Oh that could be. Okay that's true also. That's not exactly the
case we're talking about but that's a case. But another case what
would be a ספק safek of a human בכור? bechor? A woman
had a miscarriage and you don't know if the miscarriage if it
had been forty days since conception or not. Or if it had
been less than forty days then it's not considered a birth and
the next baby will be a בכור. bechor. If it was more
than forty days it was a birth and the next baby won't
be a בכור. bechor. So there are cases where you don't know
if this human baby or this animal is a בכור. bechor. אחד
בכור אדם ואחד בכור בהמה echad bechor adam v'echad bechor beheima whether
it's a human whether it's an animal בין טהורה בין טמאה bein
tehorah bein tmeiah whether it's a cow or sheep which is a
טהורה tehorah animal or טמאה tmeiah a חמור chamor donkey which you
have to redeem with a sheep. Okay in all those cases here
I am
I've got this ספק בכור. safek bechor. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
mechavero alav hara'ayah.
If the כהן kohen wants to prove that this baby calf is
his or that you know I owe the five shekel
for the פדיון הבן pidyon haben let him go prove it. המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. Now when you say המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah this is such an important
גמרא Gemara stuck in the middle of this case of יחלוקו הטלית.
yachloku hatallis. Okay when we say a case like this of המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah so we don't know if
this calf is the כהן's. kohen Let's say the כהן kohen comes
and grabs the calf. Do we mean once we said המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah and it's in my possession from
this point on if the כהן kohen wants it he has the
burden of proof? Or can who is the המוציא motzi change? As
the כהן kohen sneaks into my house and steals the calf then
I become the המוציא מחברו hamotzi mechavero and I have to prove
that it's mine. There's an objective ספק safek right? It's a little
different than the טלית tallis because the טלית tallis, there's no objective
ספק. safek. Here there's an objective ספק safek who belongs who does
it belong to. So when the כהן kohen now comes and takes
it from me and I can be yelling and screaming do we
say he's a גזלן because once we've established המוציא מחברו hamotzi mechavero
I'm the presumed owner and if he doesn't prove it he's a
גזלן? Or do we say no whee-hee we remain with a big
question mark. We don't know המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'ayah is more of a less of a פסק psak that we're
פוסק paskening it's mine until we know otherwise but it's more like
of a question mark. We don't know whose it is we're keeping
out of it. Okay so if it's like we don't know whose
it is we're keeping out of it so if the כהן kohen
steals and comes into my house and steals it and takes it
from me well maybe it's his. So now you have to prove
it's yours. Okay so this is like a really important question of
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. Is it like a
פסק psak that it's mine until the other person can prove otherwise?
Now if it's a normal case like how do we know you
know David here comes and says that this wallet and all of
its contents are his? So we would also use the phrase המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. But if he were in
front of witnesses come and stick his hand into my pocket and
take the wallet we'd call him a גזלן right? No question. But
that's because there's no evidence. So there clearly if he takes that's
המוציא מחברו hamotzi mechavero where I really do have a presumption of
ownership we have no other knowledge and therefore if he grabs it
he's a גזלן. But a case where we know there's an objective
ספק safek who does this בכור bechor belong to? We have no
idea it depends when the whether it was the firstborn it's an
objective ספק. safek. Maybe there המוציא מחברו hamotzi mechavero is more of
a we're just keeping you know we're just keeping out of it.
And then if the person are you okay there? And then if
the person grabs it the other person he actually we would also
let him keep it. So that's going to be the question here.
Yes Charlie.
So why does that particular כהן kohen have any right to it?
I mean you have okay so that's a good question and תוספות
Tosafot says תוספות says even if it belongs to כהנים kohanim I
should be able to demand it back because I have a right
to decide which כהן kohen to give it to. So תוספות says
no the כהן kohen could then say I will pay you that
benefit you have though for deciding which כהן kohen to give it
to is worth five bucks here's five bucks. Okay so anyway תוספות
asks that question but let's just bracket that. Okay? All right so
this is the גמרא's Gemara so this is the question about in
a case of like an objective ספק safek how do we see
what המוציא מחברו? hamotzi mechavero? And that is a very different way
of looking about the טהרות Taharos case about תפס אחד בפנינו. tafas
echad bifneinu.
Both guys are holding onto it. But it's not like we knew
it was one of theirs to begin with. It was a מציאה.
metziah. Neither of them had it to start with. So we like
have just a big question mark here. So maybe like we're more
taking sort of like I said before about the boat like כל
דאלים גבר. kol d'alim gevar. Like we're only going to split it
like if you know we don't know we're happy to stay out
of it. You know so if one guy grabs it and it
resolves itself that way fine let it resolve itself that way. If
one guy doesn't grab it and they both remain holding on then
we'll have to get involved and we'll have to. split it. So
it's very interesting to think about all of these cases that we've
been dealing with, because you know all these cases, how does בית
דין Beis Din פסקן paskin when it admits that it doesn't know?
I was once thinking about I think some I might have stole
this idea from somebody but anyway the idea about giving a class
called like about you know like how to live with doubt. And
the question would be about about some things like רוב rov and
חזקה chazakah and I
think I told you that before because you know so much of
הלכה halacha is we talk about it being religious stuff but so
much of הלכה halacha is you have to live your life and
you don't know right you have to and הלכה halacha guides you
through lack of knowledge. What does בית דין Beis Din do when
they admit we really don't know but you know they're coming in
front of us they're asking for a judgment? So that's a different
way of looking at this. We'll say יחלקו yachloku if we're forced
to but maybe if it resolves itself some other way געזונטהיי, gezunta
hey, you know we don't know what's going on here. Anyway that's
the case here. So let's take a look. ספק בכורות, Sfeik bechoros,
אחד בכור אדם ואחד בכור בהמה בין טהור בין טמא המוציא מחברו
עליו
הראיה. ech bechor adam ve-ech bechor behema bein tahor bein tamei hamotzi
mechavero alav hara'aya. ותניא לה, Ve-tanya lah, okay and we assume that
means that if the כהן kohen grabs it he also gets to
keep it.
ותניא לה Ve-tanya lah and we taught a ברייתא braisa on
this, I lost my place, אסורין בגיזה ועבודה. asurin begiza ve-avoda. Even
if the כהן kohen doesn't grab it
I am not allowed to shear it and I am not allowed
to work it. Why? Because even though I keep it it might
be genuinely
the בכור bechor if it's like a calf and I'm not allowed
to work or shear a בכור. bechor. So what I will do
is I can שחט shecht it and eat the meat if it
has a מום, mum, okay or I can bring it as a
קרבן, korban, so it's mine but it's mine but the reason I
don't give it to the כהן kohen is because it might not
be a בכור. bechor. But even though I'm keeping it I have
to treat it as a ספק בכור. safek bechor. You got the
idea? If it really was a בכור bechor I'd have to give
it to the כהן. kohen. So but what we're sort of doing
is we're splitting the ממונות mammonus aspect and the איסור issur aspect.
From a ממונות mammonus perspective he can't prove it's his I keep
it. From an איסור issur perspective it might be a בכור bechor
and I can't misuse it.
All right so that what would that be
misuse it would be shearing it working it you know bringing if
it has if it doesn't have a blemish then bringing it then
eating it outside of the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, if it but
if it has what I could do is I could wait for
it to have a blemish and שחט shecht and eat it or
I could bring it as a קרבן, korban, okay but what I
can so I have to treat it as a בכור bechor but
it's my בכור. bechor. All right so now why is that? So
the גמרא Gemara thinks the reason is the following. Let's take a
look. What does this have to do with being מקדיש makdish something
in this case of a debate? דהכא דאמר תקפו כהן אין מוציאין
אותו מידו, De-hacha de-amar takpo kohen ein motzin oso mi-yado, here presumably
if the כהן kohen were to grab it he would be able
to keep it. That's what המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'aya means. Whoever is the person who has it he can grab
it from me and then he gets to keep it. Okay. דקתני
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Diktani hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya.
So presumably that's because he gets if he grabs it he keeps
it. וכי לא תקפו, Ve-chi lo takpo, but if he didn't grab
it אסור בגיזה ועבודה. asur begiza ve-avoda. It can't be used. So
the גמרא Gemara understands this is such a bizarre גמרא that understands
you know why I can't use this בכור bechor since since because
the reason is because since were the כהן kohen to grab it
he would be able to keep it we treat it now as
if he's grabbed it and as if he's מקדיש makdish it and
it's קדוש. kadosh. So we treat the קדושה kedusha as deriving from
the כהן's kohen ability to grab it and keep it. So if
that's what's going on there it's bizarre the obvious answer is coming
up then similarly when we're yanking over the טלית, if you were
to be מקדיש makdish it even that would be since were you
to grab it you could keep it if you're מקדיש makdish that
also works. So the same is here since the כהן kohen were
to grab it he could keep it it's like it was already
מקדיש. makdish. So that's what we think the comparison is. So the
גמרא rejects this.
אמר ליה רבה, Amar lei rabba, Rabba said back קדושת בכור קאמרת,
kedushas bechor ka-amart, you're talking about the sanctity of a בכור bechor
לא לימא לך תקפו כהן מוציאין אותו מידו, lo leimei lach takpo
kohen motzin oso mi-yado, I will tell you that if a כהן
kohen grabs it you take it back from him he's not allowed
to keep it. ואפילו הכי Va-afilu hachi אסור בגיזה ועבודה asur begiza
ve-avoda and even if you would take it away from the כהן
kohen you would say since the owner since Dov it's in his
possession he is the presumed owner and if you take it you
have to give it back. You don't get to keep it. We've
now פסקן paskin that Dov is the presumed owner, okay and you
have to give it back. Nevertheless Dov is not allowed to shear
it or to work it. Why? קדושה באה מאליה שאני, Kedusha ba
me-aleha shani, because it's just a sanctity it doesn't come from the
it doesn't emerge from the כהן's kohen ownership he's not sanctifying it
it emerges from the reality that it's the firstborn. So basically from
an איסור issur perspective this is a ספק בכור safek bechor and
it might be קדוש kadosh and you have to treat it as
קדוש. kadosh. From a from a
חושן משפט choshen mishpat and a ממונות mammonus perspective המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya and I totally own it until and
even if the כהן kohen grabs it he has to give it
back and at the same time when we're asking an איסור issur
question and not a ממונות mammonus question it's a ספק איסור safek
issur and I can't use it. All right so it is really
interesting how those two you know are like you know how ממונות
mammonus and the איסור issur issue sort of like inter you know
can be. dealt with at different levels, but that's the answer. But
as you see a core דיני ממונות dinei mammonus question that comes
up is when you פסקן pasken המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה Hamotzi mechavero
alav haraaya in a case of objective doubt, what happens if the
other guy grabs it afterwards? Have you פסקןed pasken it for the
first guy or have you just said we're just we're just stepping
back, we don't know? All right? So there is the ש"ך Shach
who's one of these major commentators on שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch חושן
משפט Choshen Mishpat wrote an entire book called תקפו כהן, Tokfo Kohen,
which is about our סוגיא, sugya, okay, to deal with this issue
about, you know, what does המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה Hamotzi mechavero alav
haraaya mean and what happens if the other guy grabs it. And
Rav Steven by the way said that they're probably not going to
be meeting until 8:40, so if some people really have to leave,
they're welcome to leave, but I'm going to get to the bottom
of the
דף. daf. Okay, so
the גמרא says like this. All right, so okay. אמר ליה רב
חנינא לרבא, Amar lei Rav Chanina le-Rava, so רב חנינא Rav Chanina
said to רבא, Rava, תני דמסייע לך. Tani demisayeia lach. I'm going
to bring a תנא Tanna that supports you. What was רבא Rava
saying?
Now I forgot.
רבא Rava says you take it from the priest.
Oh, תקפו כהן מוציאין אותו מידו. Tokfo Kohen motzi'in oto mi-yado. Right,
okay. הספקות, Ha-sfekot, wait let me just
check רש"י. Rashi. Yeah, right, that that you would be מוציאין אותו
מידו. motzi'in oto mi-yado. Okay. הספקות נכנסין לדיר להתעשר. Ha-sfekot nichnasin la-dir
le-hit'aser. So now we have animals that are a ספק, safek, you
know, every every new season when the animals give birth I have
to take all the new animals and put them in a pen
and have them walk out single file and every
tenth one is מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah of the newborn animals. Now,
let's say I have some animals that are doubtful whether
they are
a ספק בכור. safek bechor. Now we're going to see in a
minute it's not actually a ספק בכור. safek bechor. What it was
was I had a ספק safek whether I had a בכור bechor
of a donkey. And what do you do with a בכור bechor
of a donkey? You
redeem it with a sheep. Now the sheep doesn't have
קדושה kedusha because the sheep just belongs to the כהן Kohen but
it doesn't have any sanctity, the sheep that is substituted for the
donkey. So I have now some sheep that were substituted for some
doubtful donkey בכורים. bechors. Happens every day, okay. So, and they are
all newborn sheep and do they now together with my other newborn
sheep all get put together for מעשר בהמה? ma'aser behemah? Or do
I say, so here's the thing. If they were קדוש kadosh or
maybe קדוש kadosh or whatever they wouldn't be part of מעשר בהמה
ma'aser behemah but they're not קדוש. kadosh. So the only issue here
is they might belong to the כהן. Kohen. They are a substitute
for a ספק safek firstborn donkey. It's like this case. What do
you do with a ספק בכור? safek bechor? I get to keep
it. So I redeem it on a sheep because if I didn't
redeem the donkey, the donkey couldn't be used as a בכור. bechor.
And now it's a question of who owns it. Maybe the donkey
wasn't a firstborn, so I get to keep it. So I have
all of these
ספק safek פדיון בכור, pidyon bechor, whatever, substitute for the donkeys. They
might belong to the כהן, Kohen, they might belong to me, but
I'm the presumed owner. So we put them all together and I
have to take מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah and they were all firstborn,
they were all born this year, right? So we have to go
ahead and take like מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah from them, okay? So
let's take a look. הספקות נכנסין לדיר להתעשר. Ha-sfekot nichnasin la-dir le-hit'aser.
Okay,
so you take מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah from them. Now how does
this work? ואי סלקא דעתך V'ei salka da'atach תקפו כהן אין מוציאין
אותו מידו. Tokfo Kohen ein motzi'in oto mi-yado.
Now let's say a כהן Kohen were to come and this is
the question. What would happen if the כהן Kohen were to grab
it? Would he be allowed to keep it? So if the כהן
Kohen were to grab this sheep that was in substitute for the
donkey that we don't exactly know, and if he's allowed to keep
it, then that would mean that even when I'm taking מעשר בהמה,
ma'aser behemah, this animal is being conceded as a we don't know
what it is, right? I basically said this question of תקפו כהן
Tokfo Kohen is the question of when we פסקן pasken המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav haraaya, are we basically פסקןing pasken this
sheep is mine, or are we basically פסקןing pasken we don't know
what it is and we're just keeping out of it? Okay, so
here I have my nice my nice ten sheep that were all
born, I don't know why they look like sheep, anyway okay these
were all born this year, these nice ten sheep, and of them,
okay, this one here was substituted for a donkey. If we were
to say if the כהן Kohen can grab it he can keep
it, that would mean that we would be saying who owns this?
We don't really know who owns this. We would be acknowledging that
this we don't know if it's mine, if it's the כהן's, Kohen
we're keeping out of it.
If that's true, how can I take מעשר בהמה? ma'aser behemah? What
I'm really doing is I'm conceding that I have nine sheep and
one doubtful sheep, okay, so how am I taking מעשר בהמה? ma'aser
behemah? So let's take a look. ואי סלקא דעתך, V'ei salka da'atach,
if you think
תקפו כהן אין מוציאין אותו מידו, Tokfo Kohen ein motzi'in oto mi-yado,
the כהן Kohen would be allowed to keep it, so אמאי נכנסין
לדיר, amai nichnasin la-dir, why can they all go into the pen?
נמצא זה פוטר ממונו בממונו של כהן. Nimtza zeh poter mamono be-mamono
shel Kohen. Let's say this... happens to be number ten. What I
am now doing is I am taking for my מעשר בהמה maaser
behemah something which might not be my money. So if we're admitting
that we don't really know, so then it's and so how do
I use it to get out of a like religious obligation to
take מעשר maaser on the sheep if this might not be my
sheep? Okay.
So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said אם
משום הא לא תסייעא למר. im mishum ha lo tesayaya lemar. If
that's your only proof that that's not really a good proof, 'cause
I can say that sheep is considered to be in doubt. But
הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דלית ליה אלא תשעה והוא. hacha bemai askinan
kegon dleit leh ela tishah vehu. No, no, no. The reason it
works and maybe that's what I drew on the board was that
you have exactly ten. So if you have exactly ten, it can
work.
ממנפשך, mimanafshach, what's a ממנפשך? mimanafshach? If this belongs to the כהן,
kohen, then I have nine, I'm not חייב chayav in מעשר בהמה.
maaser behemah. If it doesn't belong to the כהן kohen and it's
mine, then I'm חייב chayav in מעשר בהמה maaser behemah and I
can use it, right? So if I have exactly, if I have
eleven, then we've got a problem 'cause then even without it I
have ten that needs מעשר. maaser. And if this happens to be
the number ten that walks out, I am exempting myself from מעשר
maaser by something that might not be mine. Okay, but if I
have exactly ten, then if it's not mine I'm not חייב chayav
and if it is mine I can use it. Yes.
And מעשר maaser has to work that way where it's random, you
can't just pick one.
Correct. Right. Otherwise let it be at the end, right? Okay. So
that's what אביי Abaye says.
הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דלית ליה אלא תשעה והוא. hacha bemai askinan
kegon dleit leh ela tishah vehu. ממנפשך mimanafshach either way. Okay. אי
בר חיובא הוא שפיר קא מעשר. ei bar chiyuva hu shapir ka
maaser. If it's obligated, meaning it's mine, then it's good that it's
part of the מעשר maaser process. אי לאו בר חיובא הוא, ei
lav bar chiyuva hu, if it's not obligated because it belongs to
the
כהן kohen הוא, תשעה לאו בני עשורא נינהו. tishah lav bnei asura
ninhu. You're only left with nine and you're not obligated. Okay, so
basically this is a great question. The תקפו כהן takfu kohen question
is, when we have an objective doubt and בית דין Beis Din
says המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav haraayah, are they פוסקין
poskin it's mine or they're keeping it at as it is? And
to some degree that could be the question of our משנה mishnah
as well, you know, and why grabbing might work. Okay. And here
the question is, so we want to argue that and so that's
the question, can the כהן kohen grab it and keep it? So
we want to say from the fact that I use this for
מעשר, maaser, it proves that we פסקן pasken it's mine. And אביי
Abaye says not necessarily, maybe it's doubtfully yours, doubtfully the כהן's, kohen's,
but it's a case where it's exactly ten including it. הדר אמר
אביי hadar amar Abaye and we're going to last one more case.
הדר אמר אביי, hadar amar Abaye, then אביי Abaye said לאו מידי
דאמרי. lav midi deamari. You know what, what I just said is
not true. ספקא לאו בר עשורא הוא. safeka lav bar asura hu.
If it were a doubt, you could not use it for מעשר
maaser even if you had a ממנפשך mimanafshach type of a case.
Okay, if there's any doubt, something cannot be used for מעשר maaser
even if like you would say either way it would work. How
do I know that? דתנן, detnan, קפץ אחד מן המנויים לתוכן כולם
פטורים. kafatz echad min hamenuyim letochan kulam peturim. So there's not a
case of doubt. I just have all of these sheep, okay? I
got all these sheep, okay? They're all walking through the pen, one
by one they're walking through here and each one I'm counting: one,
two, three, four, the tenth one is going to be מעשר. maaser.
I got a couple out here and then one sheep jumps back
in and gets back mixed up. Okay, now I can stop taking
מעשר. maaser. You know why? Because you're not allowed to count any
animal twice. Okay, if it's already been counted it can't be counted
again. And if I don't know which is which, okay, any next
animal might be the animal that's already been counted and it's throwing
everything off and therefore since I can't count any of them, I
basically stop doing the whole מעשר maaser process.
But weren't you supposed to put the red dot
only on the tenth?
Only on the tenth.
This is one of the ones that was counted, jumped back in
and now I so now let's say why does that work? So
one minute, ואי סלקא דעתך ספקא בר עשורא הוא, ve'ei salka deatach
safeka bar asura hu, but if it's true that you could take
מעשר maaser in a case of doubt as long as you got
your basis covered, there's a way to get your basis covered here.
ליעשרינהו ממנפשך. le'asreinhu mimanafshach. There's a way to do it, get your
basis covered. What's the way to get your basis covered? אי בר
חיובא הוא שפיר מעשר. ei bar chiyuva hu shapir maaser. ואי לאו
בר חיובא הוא נפטר במנין הראוי. ve'ei lav bar chiyuva hu niftar
beminyan haraui. Okay, if this guy jumps back in, okay, let me
continue counting and how would it work? If it's one that is
obligated in מעשר, maaser, meaning it was not one that was previously
counted, then of course it works. If it was one that was
previously counted, hold on, let me am I losing my whole audience
here?
Okay.
One minute.
Hold on, I gotta remind myself of this case. One minute.
Okay,
so what the גמרא's saying is is that as I'm counting these
ten, for every new ten that goes out, if those ten do
not have this one mixed in, then fine, I can take מעשר.
Ma'aser. If those new ten that goes out have that one mixed
in, even though I can't take מעשר, Ma'aser, you know, I'm just
trying to think we have like one minute left, but I really
want to get through this.
Alright, I think I'm it's going to be too hard. Let's just
should we do it? Do I have people for two more minutes?
Or, alright, people's still with me? Alright fine, let's do this then.
Okay, so okay so just hold on, let me just give me
just two more seconds to remind myself about this.
Okay, so the point is like this. There's a principle called מנין
הראוי. Minyan Ha'ra'uy. מנין הראוי Minyan Ha'ra'uy means that if when you
were doing the counting in theory it could have been obligated, you
could have led to being חייב Chayav in מעשר, Ma'aser, then even
if it didn't work out that way, you are exempt. So what
would be the case? The case is you had exactly ten, okay,
you had exactly ten and you were going ahead and you were
counting, and it was one, two, three and they were walking through,
and then one of them dropped dead. Okay, so the ones that
you've already counted, they're called מנין הראוי. Minyan Ha'ra'uy. They were a
counting that was fit to be completing because you had them up
here, you were in the process of making מעשר, Ma'aser, those don't
have to be counted again. Those you're exempt. If this one if
there was one or two left over after the one dropped dead,
then those would have to still have מעשר Ma'aser taken from them
from the next crop of newly born. But the ones that were
already counted when it was possible to finish the מעשר, Ma'aser, they
were part of a legitimate process, then they're exempt even if the
process gets cut short, okay. That's called מנין הראוי. Minyan Ha'ra'uy.
And then next year you would include them?
Right, next year whatever, I think they do it first a couple
times a year. So these that had already gone through and were
counted and was able to finish and then it dropped dead and
then it interrupted the process, these are exempt. Okay, these that were,
you know, that weren't counted at all, then they would combine with
the next crop of newly born animals to be counted again.
And if
you don't get any more then the remaining ones are exempt?
Right. Now, here this one jumped in. So we say I have
a way, even though it's a ספק, Safek, that ממה נפשך Mimanah
Nafshach it's good. You keep on counting for every ten. If those
ten did not have the one that jumped in, so you're חייב,
Chayav, you're מפריש Mafrish one. Let's say those ten had one of
the ones that jumped in. So those ten had one of the
ones that jumped in, so they were coming out, okay, these ten,
and this one was the one that jumped in and I didn't
know and they were coming out. So there's one, two, three or
whatever, that was a מנין הראוי, Minyan Ha'ra'uy, because that one would
not necessarily have been the one that would have come then next.
Maybe other ones would have come next. So they're exempt. Then this
one comes out, fine. Then the next ones are like also a
type of a, I guess, of a מנין הראוי, Minyan Ha'ra'uy, you
know, because they in theory could be complete except so the argument
is is that if you were to say a ממה נפשך, Mimanah
Nafshach, you would be able even with the one mixed in to
keep on going through your process, right, and because and to say
either it is מעשר Ma'aser or it's not מעשר Ma'aser but I'm
פטור Patur anyway because it might, you know, because of this מנין
הראוי Minyan Ha'ra'uy principle.
אי בר חיובא הוא, Ee bar chiyuva hu, if I have all
ten they're obligated, שפיר מעשר. Shapper Ma'aser. ולאו בר חיובא הוא, Velav
bar chiyuva hu, נפטר במנין הראוי. Niftar beminyan hara'uy. The fact that
they were counted and in theory it could have been ended in
מעשר. Ma'aser. דאמר רבא מנין הראוי פוטר. De'amar Rava minyan hara'uy poter.
אלא מאי אית לך למימר Ela mai it lach lemeimar what are
you left with saying? עשירי ודאי אמר רחמנא ולא עשירי ספק. Asiri
vadai amar Rachmana vel'o asiri safek. הכא נמי עשירי ודאי אמר רחמנא
ולא עשירי ספק, Hacha nami asiri vadai amar Rachmana vel'o asiri safek,
that even if ממה נפשך Mimanah Nafshach it'll work, it doesn't count,
doesn't matter. It has to be definitely the tenth and not doubtfully
the tenth. And any time there's a doubt, even if you could
say, look, either it's מעשר Ma'aser or I don't need to take
מעשר, Ma'aser, it doesn't matter. If there's a doubt, it doesn't work.
So the same way in this case jumping in doesn't work if
there's a doubt, if we were to admit that the animal that
we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה Hamotzi mechaveiro alav harayah is a
doubt and the כהן Kohen could grab it and we're not פוסקין
Paskening that it's mine, we're saying it might we don't know, we're
keeping out of
it, I wouldn't be able to take מעשר. Ma'aser. So this is
a very important point that when we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה,
Hamotzi mechaveiro alav harayah, even if there's a ספק, Safek, we're really
פוסקין Paskening that it's mine and if the כהן Kohen grabs it
he's not allowed to keep it. Okay, we will see you all
on...